<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at the funerall of that painfull and faithfull seruant of Iesus Christ, Mr Thomas Wilson in his owne church at St Georges, in Canterbury the 25. day of Ianuary. In the yeare of our Lord God 1621. By William Svvift, preacher of Gods Word, at St Andrevves, within the citie of Canterbury.</title>
            <author>Swift, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13251</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23546</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101737</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837543</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837543</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1869</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13251)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1869)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1010:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at the funerall of that painfull and faithfull seruant of Iesus Christ, Mr Thomas Wilson in his owne church at St Georges, in Canterbury the 25. day of Ianuary. In the yeare of our Lord God 1621. By William Svvift, preacher of Gods Word, at St Andrevves, within the citie of Canterbury.</title>
                  <author>Swift, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 22, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I. D[awson] for Fulke Clifton,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1869:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1869:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED AT THE FVNERALL OF THAT PAINFVLL And faithfull ſeruant of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> THOMAS WILSON, in his owne Church at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Georges,</hi> in <hi>Canterbury</hi> the 25. day of <hi>Ianuary.</hi> In the yeare of our Lord God 1621.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> WILLIAM SVVIFT, Preacher of GODS Word, at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ANDREVVES, within the Citie of <hi>Canterbury.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>IOSHVA 1.2.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Moſes my ſervant is dead.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>ZACHARIAH 1.5.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doe the Prophets liue for ever?</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>I. D.</hi> for <hi>Fulke Clifton.</hi> 1622.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:1869:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1869:2"/>
            <head>TO MY NEIGHBOVRS AND VERY LOVING Friends, the Inhabitants of the Pariſh of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ANDREVVES, within the CITIE of CANTERBVRY.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>ELOVED being of late requeſted by ſome of you, to Preach the Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Sermon, of that worthy Preacher of the word of God, and a lec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turer for many yeares in this Citie, M. <hi>Thomas Wilſon,</hi> a man for his ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular gift and facultie in Preaching, and worthie works which he hath penned of good note, even among ſuch as neuer ſaw his perſon in the fleſh. And of great eſteeme, among his owne people, and many others that haue profited by his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery;
<pb facs="tcp:1869:3"/>You found me readie to tender my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, as the laſt dutie of my loue, to my fellow la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourer in the Lords harueſt, and now with the Lord.</p>
            <p>But to a ſecond requeſt, made ſince by ſome, namely, to publiſh what was then deliuered; To this, I deferred my anſwere for a time, yet after a pawſe, hauing in the interim, duely conſidered, that it is a thing too common in theſe dayes, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the enemies of truth, ſecretly, and cunning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to depraue ſuch after their death, who haue beene worthie inſtruments of Gods glory, in the time of their life, and that by the publiſhing, of what was then ſpoken of him, many abroad may truely vnderſtand the excellent reſolution of this faithfull Paſtor, the watchfull eye he hath had alwayes ouer his flocke, his conſtancie in the truth, peaceably, and comfortably, ſhutting vp his eyes in that Religion and Faith, which he profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in his life.</p>
            <p>And alſo on the other ſide, that others may take notice, of the vnfained affection, true zeale, feruent loue; of ſo great a multitude within this Citie to the Goſpell of Chriſt, taking to heart, the loſſe, and deprivation by death, of ſo emmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent a Teacher, who by the providence of God was planted among them, whom I may terme a painfull labourer, and withall a skilfull builder in the houſe of God.</p>
            <p>In reſpect hereof, I haue at length rather ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied others, then my ſelfe, in publiſhing by my pen, what I lately deliuered by word of mouth.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1869:3"/>
            <p>The reaſons why I haue dedicated this Sermon vnto you (my good neighbours and friends) are theſe;</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe I am perſwaded, many of you were well affected to the deceaſed, even for his meſſage ſake, as you are readie at all times, to harken to all ſuch as come vnto you in the name of the Lord. Your diligent attention to the word of God, both at home and abroad, deſerveth a due prayſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, to whom more fitting can I tender the firſt fruits of my pen, then to ſuch, on whom in my yonger yeares, I beſtowed both the firſt fruits of my miniſtery in the preaching of the Goſpell, and alſo the reſidue of my labours, even now to a riper age?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, to ſignifie hereby vnto you my thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, for the continuance of that loue vnto me your Miniſter, and Paſtor, now 30. yeares. In which loue of the Inhabitants of this Pariſh my moſt louing Father, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Thomas Swift,</hi> my prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor in the Parſonage of S. <hi>Andrew</hi> the ſpace of 22. yeares, a Preacher of Gods word among you, did not a little reioyce.</p>
            <p>Yea, I boldly affirme, vpon ſure knowledge, that in his declining age, he ioyed not more in any worldly bleſſing then in the loue of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who on his death-bed, when as it was queſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by his friends, where his body ſhould be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terred, charged his Executor in his laſt Will, in theſe very terms, that his bones ſhould reſt in that Church where his people ſo intirely loued him.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1869:4"/>
            <p>The premiſſes conſidered, I intreat you, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept this ſmall token I ſend you. And as I haue ſo many yeares paſt (as you all know) by the preaching of the Goſpell, indevoured to the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt of my power, to build you vp in the faith of Chriſt; So my prayers ſtill are, as they haue beene daily made vnto God on your behalfe, that you, and all yours, may grow in grace, and in the knowledge of Ieſus Chriſt, to the ſalvation of your ſoules, vnto whoſe bleſſed protection I leaue you.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in the Lord. <hi>WILLIAM SVVIFT.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:1869:4"/>
               <head>A SERMON PREACHED AT THE FVNERALL OF M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> THOMAS WILSON, in his owne Pariſh Church at S. <hi>Georges,</hi> in the <hi>Citie of Canterbury, the</hi> 25. <hi>day</hi> of Ianuary. 1621.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>ROM. 8.18.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>For I count, that the afflictions of this preſent time, are not worthie of the glory which ſhall be ſhewed vnto vs.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Chapter, the 8. to the <hi>Romanes,</hi> may fitly be termed, a ſtore-houſe, or treaſury of ſpirituall and heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly comforts, wherein the Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul</hi> vſeth ſundry arguments, to prepare, &amp; arme a Chriſtian againſt the ſtormes and miſeries of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent life. My Text that I haue read, hath a dependance vpon the former Verſe, wherein the Apoſtle comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the afflicted in this maner; <hi>Si cum eo patimur, vna cum illo glorificemur.</hi> If we ſuffer, ſayth he, with him, we ſhall alſo be glorified with him. His meaning is this; That if we now participate with Chriſt in his ſufferings, the time will come that we ſhall participate with Chriſt in glory.</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:1869:5"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>Ob:</hi> But here fleſh and bloud will obiect, that heauen indeed may be glorious, but the way to heauen is long, grieuous, vnpleaſant, full of troubles, feare, diſcontent, and the like, ſo that wkile we here remaine, in the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation of theſe ſorrowes, our hearts faint within vs.<note place="margin">Anſwered by the Apoſtle.</note> The Apoſtle returneth anſwere to this Obiection in the words of my Text read vnto you, not denying the bitterneſſe of the potion, but ſweetneth it with the hope of health, that will inſue vpon it; he gain-ſayeth not the troubles of the righteous to be great troubles, but yet not ſo great, as is the glory in the life to come, which is the portion and inheritance of the Saints. This is that which the Apoſtle reſolveth and determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in the words I haue read vnto you. <hi>I count,</hi> ſayth he, <hi>that the afflictions of this preſent life, are not worthie of that glory that ſhall be reuealed vnto vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Out of this anſwere of the Apoſtle, wee may gather theſe two ſeuerall Aphoriſmes, being the two parts of my Text.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The two parts of the Text.</note>Firſt, that Chriſtians are ſubiect and lyable to the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions of this preſent life.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that all the afflictions of this life, although they may be many and great, yet are not to be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the glory that ſhall be ſhewed <hi>vnto vs.</hi> And thus much for the method, order, and diſpoſition of my Text.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>For I count that the afflictions, &amp;c.</p>
               </q>
               <p>That which the Apoſtle here termeth afflictions, in the former Verſe he calleth by the name of ſufferings.<note place="margin">What is meant by afflictions.</note> By afflictions and ſufferings he meaneth all ſuch croſſes as happen vnto vs in this tranſitory life, and whatſoeuer is grieuous to our nature to beare.</p>
               <p>As the ſinnes of man are many, and of divers kinds, even ſo the wiſe and iuſt God hath his many, and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold differing corrections, according as by their ſinnes he ſhall be prouoked thereunto.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:1869:5"/>
               <p>The afflictions of this preſent time, as the Apoſtle here termeth them, they are two fold Outward, or Inward.<note place="margin">Afflictions two-fold, Outward <hi>or</hi> Inward.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Outward afflictions, when as God doth ſmite a man in his outward eſtate, in his goods, in his good name, in his credit, in the loſſe of his libertie by impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; As alſo with ſickneſſes of his body, which are many and grieuous:<note place="margin">Outward af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions.</note> And ſometimes with the vnto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſſe and evill diſpoſition of his children, ſo that after a carefull and chargeable education, when the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther looketh for pleaſant grapes, as the Prophet ſayth,<note place="margin">Iſa. 5.2.</note> he findeth nothing but wild and ſoure grapes, this is no ſmall croſſe &amp; corroſiue vnto Parents that feare God. Sometimes alſo God chaſtneth man by the death of his friends, and a people by the death of a carefull Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard, as we ſee at this preſent time.</p>
               <p>There be inward afflictions alſo,<note place="margin">Inward af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions.</note> when as man is chaſtned with the vnquietneſſe of his owne heart, trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of his Conſcience by reaſon of his ſinnes, with a continuall feare and expectation of Gods wrath to take hold on him, yea, with a reſtleſſe vexation of his owne ſoule; Theſe inward chaſtiſements, are called by ſome, ſoule-afflictions, the which of all croſſes are the greateſt, and of all burdens moſt vnſupportable.</p>
               <p>For thoſe outward afflictions before named, the Saints of God haue borne them with excellent pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, but theſe inward conflicts haue prooued too weightie for them, and they haue groaned exceedingly vnder them.</p>
               <p>How patiently holy <hi>Iob</hi> did beare all outward afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, his Hiſtory will informe you, but when he felt the heauie hand of God vpon him, in the troubles of his ſoule, then he cryed out amaine, as being wounded to the heart;<note place="margin">Iob 6.4.</note> 
                  <hi>The arrowes</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>of the Almightie are in me, the venome whereof doth drinke vp my ſpirit, and the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:1869:6"/>terrours of God, fight againſt me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Surely, theſe inward afflictions, haue carried ſo great a weight in the Conſcience of ſome men, that labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring by all meanes to be rid of this yoke and trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome burden,<note place="margin">Nulla poenae gravior quam poena Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae. <hi>Iſidorus.</hi>
                  </note> &amp; not knowing how, they haue laid vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent hands vpon their owne life; many ſuch fearefull Tragedies haue beene acted vpon the ſtage of this world.</p>
               <p>Beloved,<note place="margin">The Saints on earth, ſubiect to outward and invvard afflictions. Confirmed by example of Patriarkes, Prophets, and Apoſtles.</note> to theſe afflictions, both outward and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, the Children of God are ſubiect in this preſent life. <hi>Iacob</hi> the Patriarke, you ſhall finde complaining of a weariſome Pilgrimage, for when as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded what was his age, he anſwer'd, <hi>an hundred and thirtie yeares,</hi> and withall informeth him of his ſorrows,<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 47.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Few and evill haue beene the dayes of my Pilgrimages.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Elias</hi> alſo a famous Prophet of God, with a bitter complaint to heauen, intreateth the Lord to end his Pilgrimage, as being no longer able to indure the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions of <hi>Iezebel,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 King. 19.4.</note> 
                  <hi>It is enough, O Lord, take my life, for I am no better then my Fathers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Paul</hi> alſo, after his converſion to the Chriſtian faith, paſſed along in a-like weariſome Pilgrimage, and although the ſtatutes of Chriſt were his ſongs in the houſe of his Pilgrimage, Preaching the Goſpell to <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Gentils,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.20.</note> and to all men, that <hi>by all meanes he might ſaue ſome;</hi> Yet in complaints he commeth not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind <hi>Iacob,</hi> nor <hi>Elias,</hi> neither Patriarkes nor Prophets, <hi>If in this life onely we haue hope in Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.19.</note> 
                  <hi>then</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>we are of all men moſt miſerable.</hi> I referre you to his reaſon in the 36. verſe of this Chapter,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.36.</note> 
                  <hi>For thy ſake we are killed all the day long, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now concerning inward afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the mind, trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of conſcience, feare of Gods wrath before mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, it is apparant that Gods children are not exempted nor priviledged from them, beſides the example of <hi>Iob</hi> before named, I will inſtance onely in the Prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:1869:6"/>whoſe complaints are as Symtoms of the ſickneſſe of his mind, which are theſe;<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 130.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Out of the deepe haue I called vnto thee O Lord.</hi> Againe,<note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 25.7.</note> 
                  <hi>O remember not the ſinnes of my youth.</hi> Againe,<note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 88.15.</note> 
                  <hi>I am afflicted, and at the point of death. From my youth I ſuffer thy terrours, deſpairing of my life.</hi> Laſt of all, in another Pſalme demanding of himſelfe a reaſon of this agony.<note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 42.5.11.</note> 
                  <hi>O my ſoule why art thou ſo diſquieted within me, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now ſeeing that ſuch are the afflictions of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent life, and that ſuch maner of perſons are ſubiect vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, to which might be added many moe examples of the Scripture, yea, and Eccleſiaſticall ſtories will af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford many Preſidents of like nature, of Gods people ſuffering vnder many Heatheniſh Emperours, in the Primatiue Church, and ſince alſo vnder Turkes and Savages, and vnder the perſecution of Antichriſt, that man of ſinne, of whom it is written,<note place="margin">Reu. 17.6.</note> 
                  <hi>I ſaw the Strumpet drunken with the bloud of Saints.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Seeing then that the afflictions of this preſent life, doe fall into the lot of the righteous, whereof wee haue <hi>a cloud of witneſſes.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 12.1.</note> This may ſerue, to ſhew ſome men their errour,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Vſe."/> and withall to reproue them for the ſame, that if at any time they come vnder any bitter afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of this life, they ſinke in deſpaire,<note n="*" place="margin">Yea plunged into the gulfe of deſpaire.</note> and ſpare not to ſay, that God hath forſaken them, they are dam'd, and caſt away, giuing hereby very great advantage vnto Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, the common Adverſary,<note place="margin">Satan playeth vpon advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.</note> who laboureth by his ſuggeſtions to barre them of all comforts.</p>
               <p>O fooliſh and ignorant man,<note place="margin">A cauſeleſſe deſpaire re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued.</note> as thou art a man, <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil humania te alienum puta,</hi> thinke not that to be ſtrange in thee which is common to all men: as thou art a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and a regenerate man, Chriſt Ieſus hath inveſted thee into the ſorrowes of this life; you (ſayth Chriſt) to his owne, <hi>ſhall weepe and lament, and the world ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 16.20.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The Armes of the Church militant, is the <hi>Croſſe.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Armes of the militant Church.</note>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:1869:7"/>The motto of the Church,<note place="margin">The Motto of the militant Church. 2 Cor. 5.4.</note> as one ſayth is this. <hi>I doe well and ſuffer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Indeed</hi> (ſayth the Apoſtle) <hi>we that are in this Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, ſigh, and are burdened.</hi> If thou wilt conſult with the Scriptures, they will informe thee, that<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 34.19.</note> 
                  <hi>great are the troubles of the righteous;</hi> yea, and that<note n="b" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.12.</note> 
                  <hi>all that will liue godly in Ieſus Chriſt, ſhall ſuffer perſecutions.</hi> And<note n="c" place="margin">1 Pet. 4.17.</note> 
                  <hi>that Gods iudgements begin at his owne houſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Prov. 3.11.</note> 
                  <hi>My ſonne</hi> (ſayth <hi>Salomon</hi>) <hi>deſpiſe not thou the chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zinges of the Lord, for the Lord will correct ſuch as he loueth.</hi> This is a ſentence of great note and vſe in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. I find it recommended by Chriſt to the Church of the<note n="e" place="margin">Rev. 3.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Laodiceans,</hi> and alſo by the Apoſtle it is preſſed home to the Hebrewes with this amplification,<note n="f" place="margin">Heb. 12.5.</note> ſeeing <hi>that God chaſtneth whom he loueth, and ſcourgeth euery ſon that he receiueth, if a man be without all corrections, whereof</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>all are partakers;</hi> this immunitie and freedome cauſeth ſuſpition in deed,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.8.</note> that the ſame man cannot be the true child of God.</p>
               <p>I deny not but that afflictions, and the croſſes of this life, may be counted tentations, and they that with pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience beare them, of ſuch it will be ſayd in the laſt day.<note n="g" place="margin">Luk. 22.28.</note> 
                  <hi>Theſe are they that haue continued with me in tentations, and I appoint vnto them a kingdome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And out of queſtion,<note place="margin">Afflictions are great tentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but not the greateſt.</note> great afflictions are great tenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but not the greateſt of all. The greateſt of all tentations (ſayth a learned Father) is never at all to be tempted, which he groundeth vpon that ſaying to the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> that he which is without all corrections is a<note n="h" place="margin">Heb. 12.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Baſtard and no ſonne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The holy Diſciples of Chriſt, through the midſt of theſe afflictions found a paſſage to Gods kingdome. We muſt,<note place="margin">Act. 14.22.</note> ſay they, through <hi>many afflictions enter into the kingdome of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If any man ſhould inquire the way to that Citie, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards which he travelleth, if it be truly anſwered him
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:1869:7"/>thus, That the onely way to the ſame, is through many Deſerts, ſteepie Mountaines, after that he muſt paſſe by dangerous waters, and then by rough wayes, and the like.</p>
               <p>This paſſenger going on in his travell, hee findeth moſt pleaſing, delightful, and ſmooth wayes, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in no cauſe of feare, or diſcontent. Will he reioyce in this? Nay, hath he not cauſe by theſe pleaſant paſſages to ſuſpect that he hath vtterly loſt his right way. Even ſo fareth it with a Chriſtian that is bound for the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God, Chriſt Ieſus hath giuen vs the markes of the way, not eaſe, pleaſure, profit, or the like,<note place="margin">The falſe way.</note> that man who aboundeth in all theſe may iuſtly feare, that he is cleane out of the way.</p>
               <p>The true markes of the way to the Citie of God the new <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Markes of the way to the Citie of God.</note> by the report of Chriſt are theſe;<note n="a" place="margin">Ioh. 16.20.</note> 
                  <hi>Wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, lamentations, ſorrowes,</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Luk. 21.16.</note> 
                  <hi>trechery of friends,</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Luk. 21.17.</note> 
                  <hi>hatred of the world,</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Math. 23.34.</note> 
                  <hi>perſecutions,</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Rev. 2.10.</note> 
                  <hi>the Priſon,</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Ioh. 16.2.</note> 
                  <hi>Excommunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Ioh. 16.3.</note> 
                  <hi>death, martyrdome,</hi> and the like.</p>
               <p>If in theſe thou haue thy portion in this life, comfort thy ſelfe, for therein thou haſt the markes of the true way before thee.</p>
               <p>When as the Wiſe-men came from the Eaſt, and ſought after Chriſt, they had the ſtarre for their guide, of whom it is thus written,<note n="h" place="margin">Math. 2.10.</note> 
                  <hi>When they ſaw the ſtarre,</hi> (the marke of their way) <hi>they reioyced with an exceeding great ioy.</hi> Even ſo the Saints, and holy Martyres, being well taught and grounded in the truth, and bound for the kingdome of God; when as in their paſſage they met with thoſe markes, whereof Chriſt before ſpeaketh, they were full of ioy in all their tribulations, ſinging of Pſalmes, clapping of their hands, kiſſing the ſtake; for by theſe tokens and markes, they were well aſſured, that they were in the very high way, leading to the kingdome of God.</p>
               <p>But let me in the next place miniſter ſome inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:1869:8"/>to ſuch as are vnder the afflictions of this preſent life.<note place="margin">Neceſſary in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s given to ſuch as are afflicted.</note>
               </p>
               <p>It is very neceſſary that the afflicted doe vnderſtand who it is that hath ſmitten them,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                  <note place="margin">The Lord ſmiteth.</note> 
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Hoſ. 6.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Come</hi> (ſayth the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet) <hi>let vs returne to the Lord, He hath ſpoiled vs, He hath wounded vs, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Iob 33.16.</note> 
                  <hi>Elihu</hi> did truely anſwere <hi>Iob, That all corrections are ſealed of God.</hi> Aſcribing the ſame to God, as being his owne abſolute proper act and deed.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Amos 3.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Shall there be evill in a Citie</hi> (ſayth the Prophet <hi>Amos</hi>) <hi>and the Lord hath not done it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If the<note n="d" place="margin">Math. 10.30.</note> 
                  <hi>hayres of mans head be numbred,</hi> as Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe teſtifieth, yea, and theſe ſhall not periſh without the will of God, then certainely greater evils cannot fall vpon man without Gods permiſſion.</p>
               <p>Aſcribe not then thy miſhaps to Fortune:<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Vſe."/> So doe the Heathen that know not God; nor wrangle too much about ſecondary cauſes. When as the complaints came to <hi>Iob</hi> againſt the<note n="e" place="margin">Iob 1.15.16.19.</note> 
                  <hi>Shabeans,</hi> and the <hi>Chaldeans,</hi> who had taken by violence all his Cattell away from him; And of a great wind that came from beyond the Wilderneſſe, that ſmote the foure corners of the houſe, which fell vpon his Children, and killed them, IOB knew all theſe to be but Gods agents, and vſed not ſo much as any murmuring ſpeeches againſt them, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſſured that God hath a ſtroke in all the afflictions of this preſent life, very wiſely and truely anſwered in theſe words;<note n="f" place="margin">Iob 1.21.</note> 
                  <hi>The Lord hath giuen, and the Lord hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away, and bleſſed,</hi> ſayth he, <hi>be the name of the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is alſo very neceſſary that man vnder theſe cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtizements,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> doe vnderſtand that his ſinnes haue prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked God to theſe evils.<note place="margin">Sinne, the cauſe of Mans troubles.</note> For when as<note n="g" place="margin">Iudg. 13.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Iſrael continued to commit wickedneſſe in the ſight of the Lord, the Lord deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them into the handes of the Philiſtimes fortie yeares.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Had it not beene for ſinne, Man had never taſted of ſorrow. God may truely ſay as much to all ſuch as
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:1869:8"/>groane vnder the burden of afflictions, as <hi>Paul</hi> did to thoſe that were in the ſhip with him;<note n="h" place="margin">Act. 27.21.</note> 
                  <hi>You ſhould,</hi> ſayth <hi>Paul, haue harkned to me, and not haue loſed from Candie, ſo ſhould you haue gayned this hurt and loſſe.</hi> So if man in the ſtate of Innocency, had harkned to the voyce of God, and not tranſgreſſed his law,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.6.</note> by eating of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden fruit, If he had remained in obedience to the great God of heauen, theſe afflictions, and croſſes, and ſorrowes of this life, had beene altogether prevented.</p>
               <p>Here is a neceſſary caveat alſo to be given to all af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> that they accuſe not God of iniuſtice,<note place="margin">God in afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting men not vniuſt.</note> for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning thine afflictions, be they what they are, thy ſinnes haue deſerued much more. And yet take this with all for thy comfort,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> that the afflictions of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent life are not alwayes iudgements,<note place="margin">Afflictions ſometimes but tryalls.</note> but ſometimes are tryalls of thy faith, loue, obedience, patience, and conſtancie in the true ſervice of God.</p>
               <p>If therefore thou find the hand of God to be heauie vpon thee, inquire by a ſtrict examination of thy ſelfe,<note place="margin">Referred to examination.</note> what the cauſe thereof ſhould be. If thy owne Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſhall informe thee of thy loue to God,<note place="margin">How this may be done.</note> and his true worſhip, and of thy holy deſires to pleaſe Cod, and that thou ſtriveſt daily againſt the corruptions of thine owne heart, and the like, then out of queſtion, thy af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions are but tryalls.</p>
               <p>But if vpon examination, thy Conſcience ſhall inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate vnto thee, a great neglect of many holy duties, and that thou liueſt in ſome ſinnes not as yet repented of then doe thou wiſely ſuſpect the worſt, that by theſe afflictions layd vpon thee, haven doth chalenge thee for the ſame.</p>
               <p>Therefore my counſell vnto thee is this,<note place="margin">Counſell, not to be reiected, or refuſed of any.</note> If vpon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirie thus made, as thou findeſt thy ſelfe to ſtand with thy God, if thou takeſt theſe afflictions to be tryalls, exerciſe all Chriſtian patience vnder them, but if for thy ſinnes, then haſten forward an vnfained reformation,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:1869:9"/>and let me anſwere thee with CHRISTS wordes in the Goſpell,<note n="i" place="margin">Ioh. 5.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Sinne no more leſt a worſe thing come vnto thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To ſhut vp this poynt,<note place="margin">The finall cauſe of the affliction of the Saints.</note> the finall cauſe of afflictions of Gods elect, is this, namely, Gods purpoſe by them to bend, not to breake, yea, where he bendeth, he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver breaketh. <hi>Elihu</hi> anſwered <hi>Iob</hi> truely, that the marke that God aymeth at by thoſe afflictions that he ſendeth vpon his owne, is<note n="k" place="margin">Iob 33.16.17.18.</note> 
                  <hi>to open the eare of man, to cauſe him to harken vnto his word. And that thereby he may cauſe man to turne from his owne enterpriſe, and that he might hide the pride of man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And by theſe corrections he intendeth to keepe backe his ſoule from the pit, and that his life ſhould not paſſe by the ſword.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this well agreeth that ſaying of <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">1 Cor. 11.32</note> 
                  <hi>We are chaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of the Lord, that we ſhould not be condemned with the world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus much of the firſt part of my Text.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:1869:9"/>
               <p>The ſecond Aphoriſme followeth, which is this;<note place="margin">The ſecond Aphoriſme.</note>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That all the afflictions of this preſent time, although they be many and great, yet are not to be compared to the glory that ſhall be ſhewed vnto vs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I count</hi> (ſayth the Apoſtle) <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>The Rhemes Teſtament readeth it thus, <hi>I doe thinke that the afflictions of this preſent time,</hi> but <hi>to thinke,</hi> leaueth it to vncertaintie.</p>
               <p>The originall word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Statuo. Beza Repeto Zuinglius Arbitror Trimelius. Exiſtimo vulg. latin.</note> is better by learned Interpreters, tranſlated thus; <hi>I count, &amp;c.</hi> As if the Apoſtle ſhould haue thus ſayd, I haue ſummed vp to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether all the ſorrowes and afflictions of this life, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving firſt examined every particular, I count what I finde, for by experience I know what they are, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that they will not hold weight with that glory that ſhall be revealed to the Saints in the life to come.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Non ſunt paria,</hi> ſayth <hi>Beza,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Non ſunt paria. Beza. Pares paſsiones. Trimelius.</note> If you put them all into the Balance, they will proue too light, much like to that of <hi>Iob,</hi>
                  <note n="m" place="margin">Iob 6.2.</note> 
                  <hi>Oh that</hi> ſayth he, <hi>my griefe were weighed, and my miſeries were layd together in the Balance, for it would be heavier then the ſand of the Sea, &amp;c.</hi> Even ſo, if all the troubles of this life were balanced with heavenly ioyes, they would proue much lighter then the ſame. Which Metaphor the Apoſtle alſo vſeth in his Epiſtle to the Corinthians,<note n="n" place="margin">2 Cor. 4.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Our light afflictions</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>which are but for a moment, cauſeth vnto vs a farre more excellent, and an eternall waight of glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When as <hi>Paul</hi> was taken vp into Paradiſe, he ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of himſelfe, that he there heard (<note n="o" place="margin">2 Cor. 12.4. <hi>Beza.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>Ineffabilia verba,</hi> ſayth the Latin tranſlation, Words not poſſible for man to vtter. No doubt but it was a
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:1869:10"/>more harder taske to expreſſe what was then ſeene, I meane the glory of God, then to vtter thoſe words that were ſpoken vnto him.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Peter</hi> calleth the ioy of Heaven begun here on earth,<note n="p" place="margin">1 Pet. 1.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Gaudium ineffabile,</hi> You doe beleeue, and <hi>reioyce</hi> ſayth he, <hi>with ioy vnſpeakeable and glorious.</hi> If heavenly ioy, in the heart of the Saints, when as it is but begunne, while it is but in the bud, when man hath but a little taſte of the ſame, by the worke and operation of the Spirit of God, be <hi>Gandium ineffabile,</hi> that is, vnſpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ioy, how vnable is man to expreſſe the perfection of it, even that glory, ſayth my Text, <hi>that ſhall be revealed vnto vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Paul</hi> alſo to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> doth much magnifie this glory, but he explaneth it not;<note n="q" place="margin">1 Cor. 2.9.</note> 
                  <hi>The things</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>which eye hath not ſeene, neither eare hath heard, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther came into mans heart, are which God hath prepared for them that loue him.</hi> Yea, he proueth the truth hereof by Scripture,<note n="r" place="margin">Iſa. 64.4.</note> 
                  <hi>according,</hi> ſayth he, <hi>as it is written,</hi> but not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining the excellencie of this glory, by reaſon, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration.</p>
               <p>The Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> alſo,<note n="ſ" place="margin">Pſal. 45.1.</note> whoſe tongue was the pen of a readie writer, yet neither by pen, not by his tongue was he able to expreſſe this glory, but in generall termes,<note n="t" place="margin">Pſal. 16.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou wilt ſhew me the path of life: In thy preſence is the fulneſſe of ioy, and at thy right hand there are pleaſures for evermore.</hi> And againe,<note n="u" place="margin">Pſal. 36.9.</note> 
                  <hi>With thee O Lord is the well of life, and in thy light we ſhall ſee light, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But beloued, I marvell the leſſe that the Prophets of God, and Apoſtles of our Saviour Chriſt, haue paſſed by the deſcription of this glory which we hope for in the life to come, and without any particular illuſtration of the emminencie thereof, when as the Lord Chriſt himſelfe, praying to God his Father for this glory to be given vnto his Church, calleth it onely<note n="x" place="margin">Ioh. 17.5.</note> 
                  <hi>that glory, which himſelfe had with his Father before the world was,</hi>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:1869:10"/>but he explaineth it not. We ſhall all then know, and not before, what this glory is, when as in the life to come, it ſhall be revealed vnto vs, that is, when we are in the actuall poſſeſſion of it.</p>
               <p>For as he that ſate vpon the white Horſe (ſpoken of in the <hi>Revelation</hi>)<note n="y" place="margin">Rev. 19.12.</note> 
                  <hi>On whoſe head were many Crownes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Simile.</note> 
                  <hi>had a name that no man knew but himſelfe:</hi> So, no man know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the excellencie of this heavenly ioy, or the glory thereof, but he himſelfe onely that is crowned with it.</p>
               <p>Brethren, for my part I haue had but little time to meditate vpon this Scripture, but had I had much lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger time, I ſhould not haue beene able to haue ſatisfied you in this poynt, as by any deſcription, or demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations, to preſent vnto you the perfection of this glory, for<note n="z" place="margin">1 Cor. 2.9.</note> 
                  <hi>if mans heart cannot conceiue it,</hi> then much leſſe is mans tongue able to expreſſe it.</p>
               <p>Neither doth my Text put this taske vpon me, for the Apoſtle ſpeaketh onely of this glory comparatiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; comparing it with the croſſes and miſeries of mans life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I count</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>that the afflictions of this preſent time are not worthie of the glory that ſhall be revealed vnto vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Neither doe I ſee how the compariſon can well hold betwixt the one and the other, things finite, with that which is infinite.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 30.5.</note> The heauineſſe of the Saints, is but for a night, the ioy that commeth in the morning will be everlaſting.<note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 16.11.</note> 
                  <hi>At the right hand of God, there are pleaſures for evermore,</hi> as the Prophet teſtifieth.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Paul</hi> alſo himſelfe ſeemeth not ſo well to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue of this very compariſon, even in this very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect;<note n="c" place="margin">2 Cor. 4.17.</note> 
                  <hi>For</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>our light affliction, which is but for a moment, cauſeth vnto vs a farre more excellent, and an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall waight of glorie.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:1869:11"/>
               <p>And albeit, mans life be full of ſorrowes, as <hi>Iob</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, yet, ſayth he, withall<note n="d" place="margin">Iob 14.1.</note> 
                  <hi>it is of ſhort continuance;</hi> his afflictions then be but momentary afflictions, and the glory of heaven eternall.</p>
               <p>Vpon this hope of eternall glory, Gods children haue gone thorough (with ſingular patience) the weariſome Pilgrimage of this life. And although they haue not a little beene perplexed with the violent ſtormes of this world, yet herein was their comfort, an expectation that they had of this haven, where they ſhould enioy eternall reſt.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Paul</hi> giueth this for a reaſon, why he faynted not in his ſorrowes;<note n="e" place="margin">2 Cor. 5.1.</note> 
                  <hi>For we know</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>that if our earthly houſe of this Tabernacle be deſtroyed, we haue a buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding giuen of God,</hi> that is, <hi>a houſe not made with hands, but eternall in the heavens. For therefore we ſigh, deſiring to be clothed with our houſe, which is from heauen, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And againe, there is another difference betweene the afflictions of this life, and the glory which ſhall be revealed vnto vs, which doth not a little detract from the fitneſſe of this compariſon, namely, that theſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions are often times mixed with comfort, but hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly ioyes haue no tutch at all of any ſorrowes in them.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Peter</hi> writing to ſuch as were vnder great af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, yet in his Epiſtle mentioneth their great ioy;<note n="f" place="margin">1 Pet. 1.8.</note> 
                  <hi>You</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>doe beleeue, and reioyce with ioy vnſpeake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and glorious.</hi> And S. <hi>Paul</hi> confirmeth this truth by good experience in himſelfe;<note n="g" place="margin">2 Cor. 1.5.</note> 
                  <hi>As the ſufferings of Chriſt abound in vs, ſo our conſolation aboundeth through Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now on the other ſide, in the fruition of the glorie to be revealed, we ſhall enioy it, without any mixture of ſorrow. This glory will ſuffer no maner of eclipſe at all.<note n="h" place="margin">Rev. 7.17. Iſa. 25.8.</note> 
                  <hi>God will wipe away all teares from the eyes of his people.</hi> All which confirmeth the truth of this Text, that <hi>the afflictions of this preſent time are not worthie of the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:1869:11"/>glory that ſhall be ſhewed vnto vs.</hi> This glory which in a due time ſhall be revealed, it is no worldly glory, no vaine-glory; theſe will paſſe away as ſhadowes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſubſtance, which are lighter then the wind, they haue no weight at all in them,<note n="i" place="margin">Luk. 16.25.</note> there is no remembrance at all of earthly pleaſures when as man leaueth them, they vaniſh away, as it were, in a ſmoake, but the glory of God is ever laſting. And this is the portion and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance of the Saints, wherefore (as the Apoſtle ſayth elſe where)<note n="k" place="margin">1 Theſ. 4.18.</note> 
                  <hi>Comfort your ſelues one another with theſe words.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But principally I commend theſe words of comfort to all that are afflicted, that groane vnder perſecutions,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Vſe."/> and are diſtreſſed by reaſon of many croſſes and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries that haue taken hold on them.</p>
               <p>To all ſuch our Saviour miniſtreth the like words of comfort;<note n="l" place="margin">Math. 5.12.</note> 
                  <hi>Great</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>is your reward in the kingdome of heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This was <hi>Moſes</hi> comfort in his afflictions, as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſayth,<note n="m" place="margin">Heb. 11.26.</note> 
                  <hi>He had an eye to the recompence of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Stephen</hi> alſo the Martyr, in his afflictions, was ſupported by the meditation of this glory;<note n="n" place="margin">Act. 7.55.</note> 
                  <hi>Behold</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>I ſee the Heavens open, and the ſonne of Man ſtanding at the right hand of God, &amp;c.</hi> And this is it which <hi>Paul</hi> preſſeth to the <hi>Coloſſians,</hi>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">Col. 1.5.</note> 
                  <hi>for the hopes ſake which is layd vp for you in heaven, &amp;c.</hi> So then all the afflictions of this preſent time, are not worthie of the glory that ſhall be revealed vnto vs.</p>
               <p>Finally, if all the afflictions of <hi>Pauls</hi> time, which haue beene the greateſt that ever were, I meane the perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the primatiue Church, as Eccleſiaſticall Stories at large will informe you. If all thoſe troubles, yea, ſufferings for Chriſt, and Martyrdome it ſelfe be not worthy of heavens ioy,<note place="margin">Good vvorkes cannot iuſtifie.</note> then no other workes certainly can of themſelues merit eternall life, or procure for man
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:1869:12"/>the ſalvation of God: And ſo much for the Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Scripture.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Now touching the occaſion of this preſent meeting, ſomewhat is to be ſpoken.</head>
               <p>TO ſpeake much of little, ſayth one, needeth the helpe of Art; And certainely no leſſe Art is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in him, that intendeth to ſpeake little of much, fully and yet in few words. In which poynt, I ſuſpect I may fayle, having but little time left, and ſo plentifull a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of my ſpeech.</p>
               <p>At my comming into this Church, when I beheld the people here aſſembled, I remembred that report which the Evangeliſt giueth of our Saviour Chriſt,<note n="p" place="margin">Math. 9.36.</note> 
                  <hi>When he ſaw the multitude, he had compaſſion vpon them, becauſe they were diſperſed and ſcattered abroad, as ſheepe ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no Shepheard.</hi> It cannot be but a pittifull ſpectacle indeed, to behold a people diſtreſſed in this kinde.</p>
               <p>This being your owne caſe (my beloved) I may fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly compare your ſorrowes, to the ſorrowes of <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> lamented by the Prophet <hi>Ieremy,</hi>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">Lam. 1.1.</note> 
                  <hi>How doth that Citie,</hi> ſayth he, <hi>remaine ſolitary, that was full of people; ſhe is as a widow that was great among the Nations, &amp;c.</hi> The like ſay I to this preſent people, How commeth it to paſſe, that this Congregation lyeth deſolate, as a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting widow, without a Teacher, or Comforter, who of late, for the plentie and puritie of the Word, reioyced aboue all other Pariſhes and Villages round about her? Alas, the reaſon is ſoone rendred. You haue loſt a moſt painfull Paſtor, and a carefull Shepheard that attended you,<note place="margin">Vt Zancheus de Caelvine. Fuit optimus inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pres Scriptura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</note> A man called forth to the worke of the Lord, and plentifully inabled of God to the worke wherevnto he was called. He was a judicious Divine,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:1869:12"/>and <hi>Orthodox,</hi> ſound in the truth, excellent for inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of Scripture; a profeſſed enemy to Idolatry, ſuperſtition, and all falſe worſhip: for which he reaped the malice of ſome, but eſpecially of one who oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him to the vttermoſt of his power.</p>
               <p>But God ſoone vnmasked this Adverſary,<note place="margin">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Wilſon</hi> troubled by a falſe brother.</note> whoſe vizard being puld off, it inſtantly appeared to the world that he had the marke of the Beaſt in his forehead, and then gaue over the purſute of him, when as his owne Conſcience purſued himſelfe, ſo that forth with he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooke his friends, living, countrey, and all,<note place="margin">D. C.</note> and depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from vs.</p>
               <p>And as this true Shepheard of Chriſt was furniſhed with excellent gifts, both of Nature and Arts, whereby he was well fitted to the worke of the Miniſtery,<note place="margin">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Wilſon</hi> very laborious and induſtrious in his calling.</note> ſo was he moſt laborious, induſtrious, and diligent at all ſeaſons to Preach Chriſt. As he had receiued ten Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents, ſo he put them all out to the vſe of his Maſter. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, people find ſmall comfort in the great read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, knowledge of the tongues, skilfulneſſe in the Arts, eloquence, or in any other emminent gifts of ſuch as are placed over them, if they reape not the fruits of that learning in the publique Miniſtery of the Word.</p>
               <p>And as he was painfull and induſtrious,<note place="margin">He vvas alſo conſtant in his paynes.</note> ſo alſo was he conſtant in his labours, as God ſtill increaſed his gifts, ſo he ſtill inlarged his paynes, to the farther good of his Church, even from the time of his firſt comming to his charge, to the time of his death,<note place="margin">He vvas reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent 36. yeares vpon his charge. <hi>Geneſis. Iſaiah.</hi> The Goſpel of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi>
                  </note> having remained among you the ſpace of 36. yeares, preaching vſually in this place three times every weeke, lecturing vpon three ſeverall Bookes of Scripture; A taske of ſuch la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, eſpecially the ſame being ſo exquiſitely perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that the beſt learned haue moſt admired him. And in all his Sermons, he gaue good content to ſuch as were moſt judicious, yet ſtill ſpake to the capacitie of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:1869:13"/>the meaneſt; It is well knowne to all that knew him, that he was both an eloquent,<note place="margin">Like <hi>Apollos.</hi> Act. 18.24.</note> and a powerfull diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer of the Word.</p>
               <p>In which conſtancie of his labours, he fulfilled that ſaying of one, who would haue <hi>Imperatorem ſtantem mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri concionatorem concionantem mori,</hi> where ſhould the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour die, ſayth he, but in the field, and where ſhould a Preacher die, but in the Pulpit? meaning in the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full execution of his Miniſtery. His Sermons you ſee, were more then quarter Sermons.</p>
               <p>To his continued paynes of Preaching,<note place="margin">He was a very profitable writer.</note> I may adde theſe excellent Bookes which he hath penned, whereof Divines may make good vſe, and all ſuch as deſire a progreſſe in godlineſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
                  </label> But what need I rehearſe theſe things to you that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie know them, will not ſome reply to this Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, as one that anſwered the Orator, who earneſtly pleading for attention, was interrupred by one of his Auditors, demanding vpon what argument he would Diſcourſe. He anſwered, that it ſhould be in the prayſe of <hi>Hercules,</hi> then ſayd he, <hi>Num quis Herculem vituperat,</hi> Is there any here that diſpray ſeth <hi>Hercules,</hi> holding it a vaine labour to prayſe where none diſprayſeth.</p>
               <p>Or happily to my teſtimony of this worthy Paſtor, ſome will anſwere me much like as the <hi>Samaritans</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered the woman of <hi>Samaria</hi> concerning Chriſt, We beleeue all this, not becauſe of your report, but for that we haue heard him our ſelues.</p>
               <p>I anſwere thus,<note place="margin">Anſwered.</note> What is now ſpoken of him, at this preſent, is not ſo much for information, as for confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of what ye know and beleeue, when ye vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that others are of the ſame mind with you, but principally it is now ſpoken of him, that God may haue the glory of his workes and graces in him.</p>
               <p>If you of this pariſh doe not ingenuouſly confeſſe,<note place="margin">Ingratefull hearers repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</note> to the glory of God, the manifold benefits you haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:1869:13"/>by his watchfull labours; I ſay to you as Chriſt ſayd in defence of his Diſciples, <hi>If thoſe,</hi> ſayth he, <hi>hold their peace, the ſtones will cry out;</hi> even ſo, the very ſtones of this Church, let them witneſſe againſt you.</p>
               <p>And if any malignant ſpirits,<note place="margin">Depraving ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits cenſured.</note> ſhall after his death de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praue him, or detract from his Preaching, or thoſe his Bookes which he hath penned, all godly Chriſtians haue cauſe to ſuſpect them to be rotten at the coare, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound I meane in Religion; or elſe for their owne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiencie (the ground of malice) vnworthie to carrie his Bookes after him.</p>
               <p>When my ſelfe did viſite him in his ſickneſſe, and perceiued the great weakneſſe of his body, I counſelled him, vpon returne of ſtrength (if God ſo pleaſed) to be moderate in his paynes for a time; He anſwered me in theſe very words, Were I in health of body,<note place="margin">His reſolution to be conſtant in his labours. 1 Cor. 9.16.</note> I ſay alwayes with the Apoſtle, <hi>Vae mihi ſi non evangelizavero, Woe vnto me if I preach not the Goſpell,</hi> but in my ſicknes I know the Lord will not require it of me.</p>
               <p>But alas I ſee teares falling from many eyes,<note place="margin">A generall la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation in the Auditory obſerved. Deut. 34.8.</note> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſignes of mourning in this Auditory; to you that lament the loſſe of your Shepheard, as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did for their <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſo you for this Prophet of God, were your Shepheard to returne his anſwere from Heaven, it would be much like to Chriſts words, to the lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Women that followed after him.<note place="margin">Luk. 23.28.</note> 
                  <hi>Daughters of Ieruſalem, weepe not for me,</hi> ſayth he, <hi>but for your ſelues, and for your children,</hi> for your ſelues, I ſay, and for your children, becauſe you know not what evils may befall you, for theſe latter dayes grow evill apace.<note place="margin">Iſa. 57.1.</note> 
                  <hi>And the righteous are taken away,</hi> ſayth the Prophet, <hi>becauſe he ſhall not ſee them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But in reſpect of himſelfe,<note place="margin">For himſelfe no cauſe of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation.</note> there is no cauſe of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation, for he and all his labours are with God; He
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:1869:14"/>hath fed the flocke of Chriſt, and is gone to receiue the promiſed Crowne. He hath met with that comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble greeting of the Lord,<note place="margin">Math. 25.23.</note> 
                  <hi>Euge bone ſerve &amp; fidelis, it is well done good ſervant and faithfull, thou haſt beene faithfull in little, I will make thee ruler over much: enter into thy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ioy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as he was carefull for you in his life, ſo not care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe of you at the inſtant time of his death.</p>
               <p>Even as the Heathen Orator ſayd of himſelfe,<note place="margin">Tully.</note> that he had no leſſe regard, that the Common-wealth ſhould flouriſh after his death, then in the time of his life, or rather like vnto S. <hi>Pauls</hi> care,<note place="margin">Act. 20.29.</note> that when he departed from the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> he would haue grievous Wolues kept out, that otherwiſe would make a havock of the flocke the which he very earneſtly committed to the care and truſt of the Elders of that Church, and was the more earneſt,<note place="margin">Act. 20.38.</note> for that <hi>they ſhould ſee his face no more.</hi> Even ſo this truſtie and provident Shepheard, was ſo mindfull and carefull of you all,<note place="margin">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Wilſon</hi> very carefull of his flocke at the point of death.</note> that with his laſt dying breath, he prayed, and wiſhed all good to the Church of Chriſt in generall, but to you his flocke in ſpeciall, namely, his heartie deſire was this, that the Patrons of his Church would place ſuch a one in his roome, as ſhould be able to teach his poore flocke.</p>
               <p>And I hope that his worthie<note n="*" place="margin">Who vvere preſent at this Sermon.</note> Patrons will haue a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of you, even as they reſpect the glory of God, and for their owne honour and credit, and the rather at the requeſt of their brother deceaſed, who in the name of Chriſt craved it at their hands.</p>
               <p>Now to you his grieued flocke,<note place="margin">His grieued flocke com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted.</note> let me miniſter a few words of comfort, I ſay to you as <hi>Abraham</hi> did to <hi>Iſaak</hi> his ſonne, <hi>My ſonne,</hi> ſayth he, <hi>God will provide a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice;</hi> So,<note place="margin">1. That God will provide for them.</note> GOD no doubt will provide a Teacher for you.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:1869:14"/>
               <p>And comfort your ſelues in this, you the inhabitants of this Pariſh are not alone, but haue many abroad that doe ſhare with you in your ſorrowes,<note place="margin">2. They not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone in their ſorrowes.</note> that ſometimes were partners with you in the comforts of your Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</p>
               <p>Neither be you too much diſcouraged,<note place="margin">3. Truth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth though true Teachers be taken away.</note> though a true Teacher be taken from you, yet God hath left his Truth ſtill with you, and hath given you the ſpirit of Truth, that ſhall never be taken from you: You haue on every ſide ſuch as are both able and willing to inſtruct you;<note place="margin">4. The ſpirit of Truth abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth for ever.</note> you are well neighboured alſo by the cathedrall Church adioyning to you, whether you doe often reſort, and receiue inſtructions from divers very learned Divines,<note place="margin">5. They haue many inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters neere vnto them. <hi>Chriſts</hi> Church at Canterbury. Eccle. 3.1.</note> from whence, as from a continued ſpringing fountaine you may fetch the water of life; no ſmall benefit to this Citie, if they reſpect the welfare of their ſoules.</p>
               <p>Finally, <hi>Salomon</hi> ſayth, <hi>Every thing hath an appoynted time: And a time to every purpoſe vnder Heaven.</hi> Why then there is a time to heare, and a time to practiſe. You haue had a long time to heare, in the name of God, make it now a time to practiſe. <hi>Be not alwayes hearers,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 1.22.</note> 
                  <hi>but doers of the Word.</hi> And what ye haue heard by your learned Teacher in his Doctrine (as <hi>Mary</hi> did the words of Chriſt) ſo lay the ſame vp in your hearts.<note place="margin">Luk. 2.51.</note>
               </p>
               <p>You haue beene often, yea,<note place="margin">His hearers called vpon, to put in practiſe what they haue heard.</note> early and late called vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by your louing and beloved Paſtor, God calleth you now to practiſe what you haue learned. Let the crop and harveſt be anſwerable to that ſeed that hath beene here ſowne, certainly a plentifull ſeed, let the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect thereof be ſeene by a plentifull harveſt.<note place="margin">When to meet againe with their Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard. 2 Tim 4.7.</note> That in the end, you may meet againe with your Shepheard, who by the hand of God is now pulled away from you, of whom this remaineth onely to be ſpoken; <hi>He hath fought a good fight, He hath finiſhed his courſe, He hath kept the Faith, from hence forth is laid vp for him the Crowne of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:1869:15"/>righteouſneſſe, which the Lord ſhall giue vnto him at that day;</hi> And all this through the merits of IESVS CHRIST, to whom with GOD the Father, and the bleſſed Spirit, be all honour, glory, prayſe, and dominion, now and for ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:1869:15"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A POST-SCRIPT</hi> TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous READER, thus haue I ſet downe and preſented vnto thee my Sermon <hi>Verbatim,</hi> in the very ſame maner, ſo neere as memory doth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford me helpe, as I preached it, hoping it will be the better accepted for that it commeth forth, in the very ſame plaine habit, in which it firſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to ſo great a multitude that heard the ſame, who with lamenting hearts, accompanied his corps to the graue, the which was carried by ſixe Preachers of the word of God, whereon were fixed divers Latin Verſes, deploring the loſſe of ſo watchfull a Shepheard, the which Verſes if they had come vnto my hands, I would haue brought them forth vnto the light.</p>
            <p>Becauſe I haue given ſo free and large a teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of his labours, let me more particularly acquaint thee what they haue beene.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1869:16"/>
            <list>
               <head>The Bookes of holy Scripture expounded by <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Wilſon</hi> in his ordinary Lectures, ſince he came to his charge, were theſe;</head>
               <item>The prophecie of <hi>Haggai.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Goſpel of S. <hi>Luke.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Acts of the Apoſtles.</item>
               <item>The Epiſtle of <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Romans,</hi> which is ſince printed.</item>
               <item>And many whole Pſalmes of DAVID; As Pſalme 15. Pſalme 25. Pſalme 32. Pſalme 73. Pſalme 103.</item>
            </list>
            <p>ALSO</p>
            <list>
               <item>The 4. Chapter of <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> his firſt taske.</item>
               <item>The 3. Chapter of <hi>Ionah,</hi> in the time of a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall faſt.</item>
               <item>The 26. and 27. Chapters of <hi>Mathew,</hi> prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Sermons to the holy Communion.</item>
               <item>The firſt and ſecond Verſes of the ſixt Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> the grounds of his Catechiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, which ſince he hath printed.</item>
               <item>The 53. Chapter of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> in the time of Lent.</item>
               <item>The 15. Chapter of the 1. to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> vſuall at Funeralls.</item>
               <item>
                  <note place="margin">Vpon theſe 3. bookes were his laſt weekly Lectures.</note>The firſt 13. Chapters of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> every Sabboth morning.</item>
               <item>The firſt 29. Chapters of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> every Sabboth after-noone.</item>
               <item>The firſt 12. Chapters of S. <hi>Iohns</hi> Goſpel, every Fryday lecture.</item>
               <item>With very many other Texts of holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as the preſent times offered occaſion.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:1869:16"/>
               <item>He hath alſo written 12. ſeverall Bookes, which are printed. His laſt booke which he nameth, <hi>Saints by calling,</hi> or <hi>called to be Saints;</hi> In the Epiſtle dedicatory of the ſame, he calleth it, his <hi>Beniamin,</hi> or his twelfth and laſt Booke.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Such haue ever beene the reſtleſſe labours of this ſervant of CHRIST, who is now at reſt from his labours, and his workes haue fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed him.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Courteous Reader farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
